WILLIAM BOYER

william.boyer.nyc@gmail.com

SUMMARY

I'm a developer, architect, and team leader based in NYC. I still love coding as much as ever, but I've built up good skills at product and business thinking too.

Recently, I spent 13 years at Viacom, beginning as an individual contributor in the software-development team that builds and supports their sites and apps, and ending up leading that team.

For the last year, I've worked as an independent consultant, doing a mix of advisory work and coding. I've also done a lot of development work on my own, gaining good experience with some of the latest tools and frameworks.

EXPERIENCE

VARIOUS STARTUPS 01 / 2014 - Present

Consultant

I've advised four different startups this year on product strategy, user-experience design, and server- and client-side architecture.

BBC WORLDWIDE 05 / 2014 - 09 / 2014

Consultant

BBC Worldwide is developing a variety of direct-to-consumer digital video experiences, for both browsers and native devices. I wrote a requirements document for this effort, conducted an extensive series of interviews with vendors to assess their capabilities, and advised generally on architecture.

ADOPTIVE 01 / 2014 - 08 / 2014

Consultant

Here I integrated display ads from DoubleClick into bundoo.com. This involved PHP work to customize the Ad Code Manager plugin for Wordpress, plus JavaScript, CSS, and Modernizr work to place ads of varying sizes, in keeping with the site's overall responsive design.

I also developed provisioning scripts and an automation approach for Adoptive's infrastructure, which is hosted on AWS and managed by Scalr.

VIACOM 03 / 2011 - 10 / 2013

SVP Technology

In this role, I led the team of software developers that create and support all of Viacom's websites, games, and apps, across all of its brands – MTV, Nickelodeon, Comedy Central, and many others.

Our biggest priorities at this time were the consolidation and modernization of our content management systems, and improved support for connected devices, via both native apps and responsive web design.

Throughout, we continued to enable our audiences to engage digitally with a steady stream of TV premieres, tentpole events, and sponsor campaigns.

VIACOM 10 / 2000 - 03 / 2011

Software Developer, Director, and VP

Earlier at Viacom, I worked in and led various parts of our digital software-development team, sometimes focused on individual properties such as nick.com and mtv.com, and sometimes on platform projects. Some highlights:

- Managed Viacom's first integrations with Akamai, and devised a way to use ESI to achieve good caching efficiency
 even in contexts where some content is personalized.
- · Led the implementation of a major deal with Virgin Mobile, in which MTV-branded WAP, SMS, and ringtone

- content was offered exclusively to their subscribers.
- Implemented an artist-based subscription platform for MTV and VH1, allowing users to receive email and SMS alerts when new content about their favorite artists was published.
- Helped add movie data from AMG (now Rovi), and showtimes/ticketing data from MovieTickets.com, to mtv.com and vh1.com. Implemented geo-based search capability for showtimes.
- Implemented an algorithm for picking the best thumbnail image (for a video, article, artist, etc.) from a list of candidates.
- Led the build of an all-Flash, video-centric version of mtv.com. The site wasn't successful, but I learned a lot from the experience.
- Did extensive front-end and back-end work to optimize the presentation of video playlists and photo flip-books on mtv.com, vh1.com, and cmt.com.
- Led web development for many special events, including the VMAs and other award shows, the Hope for Haiti Now special following the 2010 earthquake, and the 2009 blackout on Time Warner Cable.

VARIOUS COMPANIES

01 / 1997 - 10 / 2000

Contract Software Developer

During this period I did contract software development for a number of firms, both established and startup, the most notorious of which was UrbanFetch, where I wrote key components of their payment processing and order fulfillment pipeline in Visual Basic.

I also prototyped an application for capturing and analyzing business strategy, in Visual C++.

TROUT TRADING

03 / 1993 - 01 / 1997

Software Developer

Trout was a commodity futures trader that started out in Chicago but moved offshore to Bermuda and Toronto. I was a research analyst there, responsible not only for analyzing historical datasets and developing new (primarily technical) trading strategies, but also writing all the code (in C++ and S) to backtest and implement them in production. I was moderately successful at the research part of that job – which today might be called "data science" – but I always preferred the coding part.

BATTERYMARCH FINANCIAL MANAGEMENT

06 / 1988 - 03 / 1993

Software Developer

Batterymarch is an equity investment fund manager. There I led a small team developing a suite of portfoliomanagement applications for X11 on Unix workstations, written in Objective-C — pre-Apple, pre-NeXT.

BDM INTERNATIONAL, INC.

05 / 1985 - 08 / 1987

Software Developer

My work at this defense contractor was in Pascal and C, for an intelligence client and for NASA. The NASA app was written in C for MS Windows 1.0!

EDUCATION

MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY

1987 - 1988

Economics

UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND COLLEGE PARK

1982 - 1986

Bachelor of Science (BS), Computer Science

UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND COLLEGE PARK

1982 - 1986

Bachelor of Arts (BA), Economics